Finding Aid for Frank D. McKay Papers, 1909-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank D. McKay Papers 1909-1965
McKay, Frank D., 1883-1965.
851800 Aa 2; AC
Grand Rapids, Michigan businessman and politician; correspondence, business papers; scrapbooks, and photographs.
3 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from the estate of Frank and Agnes McKay (donor no. 5176 ) in December 1971.
The collection is open to research.
Born in Grand Rapids, Michigan on November 4, 1883, Frank D. McKay left school to work in various manual labor jobs. He was a natural businessman however. As many of his fellow workers were foreign born, McKay set up a small foreign money exchange business for them. He also established a private banking and investing business for these workers. Later on, he became an agent for a number of steamship lines and then branched out into the construction and financing of homes in the Grand Rapids area.
Early in his career, Frank McKay became involved in politics, organizing his friends and associates to back local candidates. He sought no office for himself until 1906 when he was appointed deputy county clerk and assignment clerk for the local circuit court. With his organizational skills, McKay built up an organization that gained control of the Kent County Republican Party, eventually becoming county chairman. Based upon his performance and growing power as a politician, McKay was elected state treasurer in 1924. He was twice re-elected, but did not seek a fourth term in 1930.
McKay preferred working behind the scenes of party politics, using his influence throughout the 1930s at state party conventions. In 1940, he was named a delegate to the Republican National Convention where he was a floor manager for Wendell Willkie. Following the convention, he served as a member of the Republican Party National Committee. At this time, McKay began to face legal problems. He was indicted in federal court in Detroit on charges of graft and conspiracy in connection with purchases by the State Liquor Control Commission. Although acquitted in 1942, these charges were brought in state court in 1944. McKay was again acquitted. Even so, McKay's political fortunes waned. He was removed from the Republican National Committee in 1944. He also lost control of the Kent County Republican organization to a local independent Republican group who called themselves the Home Front. And in 1950, a Citizens Action movement wrested control of Grand Rapids city government away from McKay and his political allies.
McKay remained successful as a businessman, owning and adding on to the Grand Rapids National Bank building, operating an insurance and realty businesses, and founding the Grand Rapids Times newspaper and acquiring the Grand Rapids Chronicle which two papers later merged into the weekly Michigan Times. He also owned a hotel in Miami Beach, Florida. He died January 12, 1965.
The Frank D. McKay collection is divided into the following series: Correspondence; Topical Files; Business and financial papers; Newspaper clippings and scrapbooks; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Business records.; Elections--Michigan--1958.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; McKay, Frank D., 1883-; Michigan. Dept. of Treasury.; Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Michigan--Politics and government--1917-1921.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Presidents--United States--Election--1940.; Presidents--United States--Election--1952.; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Republican Party (Mich.); United States--Politics and government--1933-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bal Harbour Hotel (Miami Beach, Fla.); Buildings--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; City and town life.; Clothing and dress--1951-1960.; Dance.; Dining rooms.; Entertainment.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Buildings.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Street-railroads.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Streets.; Hotels and taverns--Florida--Miami Beach.; Interiors.; Manners and customs.; McKay, Frank D., 1883-; Miami Beach (Fla.)--Hotels and taverns.; Photography.; Street-railroads--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Streets--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Swimming pools.
Contributors:
Adams, Sherman, 1899-1986.; Brake, D. Hale, 1891-1979; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Groesbeck, Alexander J. (Alexander Joseph), 1873-1953.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.; Jenkins, Guy H.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Mapes, Carl Edgar, 1874-1939.; Martin, Joseph William, 1884-1968.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - 1918-1939, 10 folders (Box 1)
- Topical file
  - Republican National Committee 1940-1944 (Box 1)
  - Blue Water Bridge 1939 (Box 1)
  - Testimonial dinner held for McKay 1942 (Box 1)
  - Lincoln Day Banquet programs 1932-1950 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea 1920-1957 (Box 1)
- Business and financial papers
  - 1909-1917, 10 folders (Box 1)
  - 1918-1923, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Newspaper clippings and scrapbooks
  - Newspaper clippings 1920-1965, 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Republican politics 1918-1924 (Box 2)
    - McKay's business and political activities 1912-1924 (Box 2)
    - McKay trial 1940-1942 (Box 3)
    - Republican politics 1939-1946
      - 1939-1940 (Box 3)
      - 1944-1946 (Box 3)
    - McKay's activities 1944-1946
      - 1944-1946 (Volume 1)
      - 1946-1965 (Volume 2)
- Photographs
  - Grand Rapids buildings and street views (Box 3)
  - Photograph Album, 1955-1957 (Box 3)
  - Photograph Album, 1957-1959 (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Adams, Sherman, 1899-1986.
1958, Dec. 28, 1959, Jan. 1960
Brake, D. Hale, 1891-
Nov. 29, 1954, Dec. 10, 1954
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.
Sept. 19, 1932, 1956
Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.
July 30, 1942
Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.
June 1955
Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.
1939
Farley, James Aloysius, 1888-
1942
Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.
Jan. 4, 1935, Nov.12, 1936, Dec. 21, 1936, Aug. 29, 1938
Groesbeck, Alexander J. 1873-1953.
Oct. 14, 1924, July 8, 1948
Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.
Aug. 28, 1958, Sept. 12, 1958
Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.
June 2, 1942, Mar. 27, 1944
Jenkins, Guy H.
May 28, 1952, June 9, 1952
Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.
June 13, 1961, 1960
Mapes, Carl Edgar, 1874-1939.
Jan. 12, 1918, Nov. 14, 1918, Nov. 21, 1934, Nov. 9, 1936
Martin, Joseph William, 1884-1968.
1940, May 5, 1941, Feb. 13, 1942, June 3, 1942
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860
Oct. 9, 1934, Mar. 16, 1935, Dec. 23, 1935, Sept. 26, 1938, Oct. 5, 1938, May 14, 1940
Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.
June 6, 1952, Jan. 16, 1953
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
June 8, 1932, Dec 5, 1932, June 1936, June 2, 1942, Dec. 18, 1942, 1944, Nov. 22, 1949, Sept. 1950
Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
Aug. 31, 1940